<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chris Bamborough</title>
    <description>The personal website of Chris Bamborough</description>
    <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.chrisbamborough.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 16:24:11 +1100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 16:24:11 +1100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Running out of STE(A)M</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In October, I presented at the Australian Architectural School Association (AASA) conference. The title for the event was “Project to practice: Innovating Architecture” and focused on two major questions, where is architecture creating its future, and how is the sector shaping the policy and funding levers of tomorrow? I submitted a paper entitled “Running out of STE(A)M: A Critical Perspective on the Political Rhetoric of Innovation” and presented a twenty-minute summary. The paper argued that political power, in particular, the Australian Turnbull Government, used innovation as a political tool. New economic policy proclaimed that democratised innovation would distribute wealth and continue Australian economic growth beyond the resource boom. I sought to uncover the assumptions and hidden strategies that lie in the use of innovation towards increasing corporate and institutional access, acquisition and control of knowledge. The paper aimed to demonstrate that the paradigm of resource manipulation, where a perceived scarcity and market demand drives the price of natural materials, had been transferred onto the realm of data, information and knowledge, or as McKenzie Wark puts it, had created a “vectorization of information”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6c2b9755&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6c2b9755&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This vectorisation represents a placement of capitalist ideology, property ownership and market based value extraction, onto an abundant resource. I am personally critical of capitalism for its rampant need for “growth” and “progress” which translates into the unethical exploitation of the biosphere for profit generation. I’m also critical of the unequal distribution of wealth capitalism has produced and its boom to bust cyclic nature that governments treat as a necessary evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name “Running out of STE(A)M” was a response to the Australian government’s “Ideas Boom” policy that sought to increase Science, Technology, Engineering and Maths in schools, with the aim of increasing innovation in the future. My main critique was in the loss of Art as a necessary connection back to everyday life, and a counter to the observed trend of innovation for innovation’s sake within STEM. When art is compared within a framework of efficiency, productivity and return on investment, it cannot compete. The creative and cultural industry provided $86 billion in 2014 but only contributed 6.9% of the overall GDP (ABS), as a result many Australian states have cut arts funding. An economic lens applied to a critical cultural driver misses what art’s role is in society, to provide means of understanding and interrogating our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only culture that the ideas boom referred to was tech startup and entrepreneurial culture, to which my paper was also critical. The US has shown how important tech innovation and startups can be in generating wealth, and how important entrepreneurial thinking is towards this. Subsequently, every government wants to replicate a version of Silicon Valley. This is problematic as beyond economic success it has show to have issues with elitism&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:c0ea01a0&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:c0ea01a0&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, sexism &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2f21c4b7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2f21c4b7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and racism &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bc14eba3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bc14eba3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in its drive to make the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The promotion of start up culture and STEM in schools redistribute the pressures of business and drive for profit into an environment which should support free exploration and discovery. The promoted vision that entrepreneurs, startups and tech innovation can lead to fame and wealth a la Musk or Zuckerberg, should not be a driver of knowledge generation at school level. Rather than conforming to an existing political and financial system it should provide opportunity to imagine something better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas around the paper referred heavily to Goodbun, Klein, Till and Rumpfhuber’s enlightening book “The Design of Scarcity” &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:b1129747&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:b1129747&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that describes how architects help to maintain a capitalist system of scarcity and desire, within the built environment, I thoroughly recommend it. Energy directed towards architectural design and innovation is absorbed by forces of capital generation, and subsequently decisions towards built outcomes are made by those with the economic means of development and aligned towards maximising profit. On large commercial projects, the architectural profession has found itself simply engaged to maximise gains through generating value in the building as a commodity. “Value Engineering” has become the driving parameter of spatial outcomes and the socially aligned profession of architecture, becomes subservient to corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper concluded with some ways that architects could avoid being complicit in capitalism’s misfortunes. In summary, it looked at how architects could move towards socially concerned development, realign design focus away from buildings as commodities, and shift the mindset to celebrate the abundant rather than controlling scarcity. As Carlo Ratti and others have proposed architects should redirect their innovative energy towards developing an ecological view of buildings, its ambition should be to generate value through the processes and relations that come before and after a built outcome. New technologies such as the blockchain can provide ways to develop alternative sources of revenue through fostering community and social use value. This could help circumnavigate markets monopolised and controlled by those with access to capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Rifkin in his book Zero Marginal Cost Society &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:f5c544bb&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:f5c544bb&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; convincingly describes how abundance will soon become a condition due to innovation within our energy, communications and transport infrastructures. This abundance does not benefit from exclusive access and control, it wants to be shared, but this is a hard financial relationship to convince architects. Professional practices are forced to protect their work and ideas in an economy that rely on property law and resource ownership. Ideas and knowledge are an abundant resource, but this energy is wasted within a system which values creativity so cheaply that it expects free entry into design competitions like it is an enthusiastic hobby. Architects need to realise that a collective pooling of resources, knowledge and ideas will reciprocate input and ultimately benefit the built environment. The creation of an architectural commons, similar to open source projects or Wikipedia, could achieve this. Peer to peer collaboration and production, where sharing is the dominant mode of operation, has been shown to thrive on social benefit rather than wealth and can allocate resources based on need rather than under economic or managerial influence &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7045553f&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7045553f&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.In such an environment of sharing, value is shifted towards the benefit of a larger group, rather than supply and demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greater digital connectivity and ethical tracking of people and things can provide empirical evidence of cause and effect, connecting action to environmental or humanitarian benefits. This I hope will help us move away from a current economic system which is unable to detect pricing impact beyond its immediate availability and current need. Sharing of architectural resources would not result in an impoverished communism where equality is forced on a collective; it is what Michel Bauwen’s refers to as “Collective Individuality” where economic gain correlates to effort placed on a greater good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism isn’t going anywhere soon, but that doesn’t mean architects have to settle for it. They should start to covertly explore alternatives, try and avoid the proprietary and profit-driven nature of neo-liberal markets forces and realign its energy towards the provision of a fair and just society with an abundance of fulfilling cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6c2b9755&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Wark, M. A Hacker Manifesto, Harvard University Press, 2004 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6c2b9755&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:c0ea01a0&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Watson, R. In Silicon Valley, Young white males are stealing the future from everyone else.The Guardian, 2016, Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/may/27/in-silicon-valley-young-white-males-are-stealing-the-future-from-everyone-else&quot;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/may/27/in-silicon-valley-young-white-males-are-stealing-the-future-from-everyone-else&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:c0ea01a0&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2f21c4b7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Revolving Door, Huffington Post, 2016, Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/lisen-stromberg/problem-with-women-in-tech-the-pipeline-or-the-revolving-door_b_6992522.html&quot;&gt;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/lisen-stromberg/problem-with-women-in-tech-the-pipeline-or-the-revolving-door_b_6992522.html&lt;/a&gt; [Accessed July 18, 2016] &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2f21c4b7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bc14eba3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Kosoff, M. Does Silicon Valley Have a Racism Problem? Vanity Fair, 2016, Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vanityfair.com/news/2016/06/does-silicon-valley-have-a-racism-problem&quot;&gt;http://www.vanityfair.com/news/2016/06/does-silicon-valley-have-a-racism-problem&lt;/a&gt; [Accessed July 18, 2016] &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bc14eba3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:b1129747&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Goodbun, J. Klein, M. Till, Jeremy. &amp;amp; Rumpfhuber, A. The Design of Scarcity, Strelka Press: Moscow, 2013 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:b1129747&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:f5c544bb&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rifkin, J., 2014. The zero marginal cost society, New York, NY : Palgrave Macmillan, 2014. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:f5c544bb&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7045553f&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bauwens, M. The Political Economy of Peer Production M. Kroker &amp;amp; A. Kroker, eds. CTheory, 2005, Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ctheory.net/articles.aspx?id=499&quot;&gt;http://www.ctheory.net/articles.aspx?id=499&lt;/a&gt; [Accessed May 9, 2016]. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7045553f&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 23:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/articles/2016/11/30/RunningOutOfSTE(A)M.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/articles/2016/11/30/RunningOutOfSTE(A)M.html</guid>
        
        <category>Innovation,</category>
        
        <category>Practice,</category>
        
        <category>Conference</category>
        
        
        <category>Articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Giga Factory and post-anthropocentric architecture</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I stumbled across a YouTube video of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-y2_eJFYZbo&quot; title=&quot;Giga Factory presentation&quot;&gt;Elon Musk&lt;/a&gt; opening Tesla’s new Gigafactory. Apart from the astonishing fanboy following Tesla seems to have acquired I was taken aback by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://architizer.com/blog/10-facts-about-elon-musks-gigafactory-the-soon-to-be-largest-building-in-the-world/&quot; title=&quot;Giga Factory visualisation&quot;&gt;visualisation&lt;/a&gt; of the future factory showing an enormous box in a desert with solar panels on top. Initially, I thought that Tesla had turned their attention towards production on Mars (that’s still reserved for SpaceX) but the barren desolate landscape, turned out to be Nevada. In Musk’s presentation, he describes the new factory as one designed to be a machine, the new facility treated as a Tesla product needing “more innovation and engineering skill than the (car) product itself”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le Corbusier was known for the statement that houses were “machines for living”, for him that meant space could imitate the efficiency of a machine towards the provision of a particular style of life. What struck me about the Giga factory was that efficiency had become the prime ambition through space, but rather than humans, it is focused towards production process and equipment. Tesla’s strategy is clever but obvious, increase density and efficiency of equipment will reduce the marginal costs of production and in turn converge towards more affordable products. Musk compares the factory to a piece of industrial design, completely bespoke and customised to the process at hand, designed as an integrated product, more specifically a “very high density, multilayer integrated circuit, an advanced CPU…super optimised for speed and density”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From his presentation, it seems that the new Giga factory, with its super dense collection of robotic production machinery and context of nothingness, is a fully autonomous facility where humans need not apply. Through a little extra background reading though it turns out there will be approximately 6,000 people working at the plant. Two interesting things for me arose from this deceleration, firstly is the consideration of what architecture for non-humans could look like, and the other is what happens to buildings when they are excessively over engineered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America’s largest tech companies have all recently buddied up with starchitects such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dezeen.com/2015/02/27/big-and-heatherwick-unveil-vibrant-new-neighbourhood-for-googles-california-hq/&quot; title=&quot;Google Campus&quot;&gt;BIG&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dezeen.com/tag/apple-campus-2/&quot; title=&quot;Apple Loop&quot;&gt; Fosters and Partners&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dezeen.com/2015/03/31/facebook-moves-into-campus-frank-gehry-silicon-valley-california/&quot; title=&quot;Ghery Facebook&quot;&gt;Frank Gehry&lt;/a&gt;, to create “campuses” or “headquarters” or “imagineer worlds” (I made the last one up). In all cases, the human (the commodifiable input into these corporate machines) provides the focus and results in spaces of work / life hybrids that bring light and nature into the office environment. What happened to factories? People still work in these environments, but it seems these can be treated merely as an extension of the manufacturing machinery it houses, and therefore becomes the presumed remit of the engineer. It seems Tesla needs to consult an architect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In considering the factory and architecture and interesting history emerges. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/AEG_turbine_factory&quot; title=&quot;AEG Factory&quot;&gt;Peter Behrens AEG turbine factory&lt;/a&gt; is known as being one of the first buildings that sought to reflect a particular company’s product base and brand. In AEG’s case, the factory was designed to communicate the domestic technology produced within, such as lamps, kettles and clocks. In 1909 production involved the combination of human skill and mechanical automation, Behren’s design took care to provide favourable working conditions for AEG’s workers with considerate light providing fenestration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the early 1900s, the factory remained the domain of architects, one of the most famous examples (due to the Italian Job) was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Lingotto&quot; title=&quot;Lingotto Fiat Factory&quot;&gt;Lingotto Fiat Factory&lt;/a&gt; by Matté Trucco which was designed around the assembly line of a fiat car including test track on the roof. Its architecture was formed around the production process, but still provided human-centric working conditions through air and light. Increased mechanisation and automation reduced the need for humans in the production process, for a potential factory worker this was financially disastrous, but for humanity, this could only be a good thing. Traditional factories are not healthy environments to be working, they can be noisy, dirty and potentially life-threatening, but it is ironic that conversions of modernist factories provide the most interesting domestic spaces due to their extraordinary scale and glass provision. At some point, the factory shifted from window adorned urban fabric to blank suburban estate boxes (or cylinder if you are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.archdaily.com/363581/factory-building-on-the-vitra-campus-sanaa&quot; title=&quot;SANAA Factory&quot;&gt;SANAA&lt;/a&gt;) fully internalising its environment through air conditioning and artificial light. Was this shift the point where the factory passed on from the responsibility of architects to that of engineers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something at the Giga factory seems to be amiss, with its 6,000 human workers there is no trace of human in its design. In theory, it can fully internalise its environment without ruining the biosphere because the sun and wind powers it, but shouldn’t humans be able to see some daylight? The Giga factory could be emblematic of a new turn towards Object Oriented Philosophy in Architecture; it has started to provide architectural justification for rejecting context and purely anthropocentric design decisions. Such a position could liberate architecture to explore new and unusual spatial types that consider human and non-human inhabitants, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tesla.com/en_AU/gigafactory?redirect=no&quot;&gt;Giga factory&lt;/a&gt; should provide a warning that if the human is removed from the equation completely, it appears architects need not apply.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 23:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/articles/2016/11/19/GigaFactory.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/articles/2016/11/19/GigaFactory.html</guid>
        
        <category>Architecture,</category>
        
        <category>Non-Human,</category>
        
        <category>Post-Anthropocentric</category>
        
        
        <category>Articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Culture Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Making Culture is a collection of thoughts and reflections related to Chris Bamborough’s PHD research into digital culture and infrastructures in Architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Making Culture project was inititated by a research travel scholarship awarded from the The Byera Hadley Travelling Fund in 2014. This enabled visits to spaces of community making in Australia and the US to study and understand the potential benefits of personal fabrication for architecture and vice versa. It was interested in how community making could potentially provide a vehicle for architects to better connect the esoteric nature of architectural design and increase public appreciation of architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project has evolved since to explore how architecture can adapt to remain relevant in todays digitally networked society, while helping to reconnect digital culture and design with the material and tectonic traditions of architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 06:45:00 +1100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/mc_about/2016/11/07/MC_About.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/mc_about/2016/11/07/MC_About.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>mc_about</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>P5.js Perlin Noise Agents</title>
        <description>&lt;script src=&quot;/js/p5Sketches/P5perlinFlowAgentsSketch.js&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/p5Objects/P5_particle.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/p5Objects/P5_flowField.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2016 05:45:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/09/11/P5PerlinAgents.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/09/11/P5PerlinAgents.html</guid>
        
        <category>Creative_Code,</category>
        
        <category>p5.js</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>P5.js Perlin Noise 3D Terrain</title>
        <description>&lt;script src=&quot;/js/p5Sketches/P5perlinTerrain.js&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 22:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/09/07/P5PerlinTerrain.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/09/07/P5PerlinTerrain.html</guid>
        
        <category>Creative_Code,</category>
        
        <category>p5.js,</category>
        
        <category>Perlin_Noise</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>P5.js Perlin Noise Flow Field</title>
        <description>&lt;script src=&quot;/js/p5Sketches/P5perlinFlowFieldSketch.js&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/p5Objects/P5_flowField.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 05:45:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/08/31/P5FlowField.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/08/31/P5FlowField.html</guid>
        
        <category>Creative_Code,</category>
        
        <category>p5.js</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Robot Trainers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As computers and robots become more capable in movement and artificial intelligence they will offer clients and developers a cheaper, more efficient and more manageable alternative to human labour. Research into the creative capacity of agents, or autonomous computation is already 15 years in the making (Saunders 2001) meaning that designers days seem numbered. Fear not fellow architects, this is an opportunity to become unshackled from AutoCAD and Revit, think of this as a chance to outsource the crap you hate, bathroom details…robot, door schedules…robot, environmental impact assessment reports…actually even the robot might find this too much. Rather than thinking of this as a them and us, it offers a new kind of approach to design and building, one where architects become robot owners, trainers, mentors. A two way relationship with a software or hardware robot provides a means of design, communication and production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;robarch-sydney&quot;&gt;Rob|Arch Sydney&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attended the Sydney Rob|Arch conference in March this year and this future was present, but through weak(ish) signals. I was the first time I had seen collaborative robots (HAL Robotics &amp;amp; Bond University), interactive 3d printing robots (Institute of Advanced Architecture Catalunya, Harvard GSD &amp;amp; University of Sydney and UNSW), and real-time vision sensing generative design robots (RMIT Architectural Robotics Lab and Southern California Institute of Architecture). The introduction of realtime communication between human, robot and material at this stage was clunky and not as “real time” as hoped, but it showed how the treatment of robots as subservient machinery through deterministic algorithms is no longer the accepted approach. While the outcomes shown at Rob|Arch were pretty wild and unpredictable, treating material behavior as an unknown in the design system, there is an opportunity for architects to understand the systems and create tunable outcomes, this is where training will come in. The progression of machine learning technology, and open source software tools mean architects with the right skills can take on the responsibility to continuously improve their own robots while engaging in the theory and practice they love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;personal-robots&quot;&gt;Personal Robots&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As software bots and industrial robots become more accessible and more manoeuvrable via Moore’s (Observation) Law, it becomes possible to imagine robot work cells maintained and constantly improved through interaction with architects, providing a liberation from the banal, and re-connecting with the built environment. It won’t mean a loss of the spatial intelligence needed to be architect, it will mean design studios, construction electives and history and theory in architecture schools will utilise personal and collaborative robots as a means to understand the past and imagine the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this scenario quality and ability will come to be measured through the architectural intelligence of robots which will reflect its human collaborators knowledge and capacity to teach. Beyond this, if the singularity is to be believed, the robot architect can take over the practice while the human architect goes and spends time with loved ones, or be killed, its hard to tell at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saunders, R. 2001 Curious Design Agents and Artificial Creativity, Ph.D. Thesis, Faculty of Architecture, The University of Sydney.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 22:00:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/articles/2016/08/30/RobotTrainers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/articles/2016/08/30/RobotTrainers.html</guid>
        
        <category>Robots,</category>
        
        <category>Fabrication,</category>
        
        <category>Practice</category>
        
        
        <category>Articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Intoduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Chris Bamborough is a designer and researcher working in the field of architecture.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This site is a collection of tool explorations and thoughts relating to his practice and research.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to venture out you can read about his professional &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linkedin.com/in/chrisbamborough&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;experience&lt;/a&gt;, scroll through his 42 character &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/chrisbamborough&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;musings&lt;/a&gt;, learn about his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.behance.net/chrisbamborough&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; in more detail, check out his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.github.com/chrisbamborough&quot;&gt;coding&lt;/a&gt; interests, watch some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vimeo.com/chrisbamborough&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;films&lt;/a&gt; he’s made, listen to his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.soundcloud.com/smoothspace&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;musical&lt;/a&gt; influences, browse his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pinterest.com/chrisbamborough&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;visual&lt;/a&gt; inspirations, connect with his &lt;a href=&quot;https://uts.academia.edu/ChrisBamborough&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; publications, or learn about his current &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com/pub/bambarooga/phdreadings&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;interests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 05:45:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/about/2016/08/02/About.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/about/2016/08/02/About.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>about</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>P5.js background interactivity</title>
        <description>&lt;script src=&quot;/js/p5Sketches/P5backgroundSketch.js&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next stage is to create p5 sketches in the background so it isn’t confined to a canvas window within the post. In this post the canvas has simply been assigned to an overall html Div called backgroundCanvas which wraps all the content. As previously the sketch canvas is given the div’s attributes as height and width.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The p5.js website integrates a background animation through an iFrame positioned to float behind, I’m not sure if this is a better solution or not. Any comments tweet me on &lt;a href=&quot;www.twitter.com/chrisbamborough&quot;&gt;@chrisbamborough&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;canvasDiv&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;backgroundCanvas&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;divWidth&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;canvasDiv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;offsetWidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;divHeight&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;canvasDiv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;offsetWidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sketchCanvas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;createCanvas&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;divWidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;divHeight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sketchCanvas&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;parent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;backgroundCanvas&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;draw&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;mouseIsPressed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fill&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fill&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;255&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ellipse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;mouseX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;mouseY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;40&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;40&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;keyIsPressed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;clear&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 05:45:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/05/11/P5Background.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/05/11/P5Background.html</guid>
        
        <category>Creative</category>
        
        <category>Code,</category>
        
        <category>p5.js</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Using P5.js with Jekyll</title>
        <description>&lt;div id=&quot;postCanvas&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; border: 1px solid black; height: 450px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;/js/p5Sketches/firstP5Sketch.js&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press any button to clear the canvas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been playing around with &lt;a href=&quot;https://processing.org&quot;&gt;processing&lt;/a&gt; for a few years now but never really got stuck in because of the difficulty to share on the web (without annoying aplets). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.processingjs.org&quot;&gt;Processing.js&lt;/a&gt; offered a way to use processing in the browser, but involved an extra layer of translation from java (processing) into javascript. Enter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.p5js.org&quot;&gt;p5.js&lt;/a&gt;, the intuition of processing but using native java script in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The P5 series of javascript &lt;a href=&quot;https://p5js.org/libraries/&quot;&gt;libraries&lt;/a&gt; provide means to play with the DOM (Document Object Model), Sound, Interaction, Data streams, Image, Video to name just a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have been playing with the P5.js IDE which has a built in web-server, but I wanted to start publishing my experiments to this site. As it is a jekyll site and posts are written in markdown I had to find a work around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do was include the p5.js libraries into the head of the Jekyll site. In header.html;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;      &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;/js/p5.js&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously in my failed ambition to replicate the Nature Of Code book using straight java script, I was pointing my javascript to an HTML canvas element in the markdown post. As P5 deals with creating a canvas itself, I simply used a div with an id myCanvas to provide a placeholder for a canvas created in javascript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll works by writing posts in markdown, which then get compiled into HTML with css styling. The great thing about markdown is that you can throw in html and javascript in amongst and it will render it to the page. As mentioned above I first needed a div for my canvas, then a link to my .js sketch file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;myCanvas&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;/js/p5Sketches/firstP5Sketch.js&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;text/javascript&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the .js sketch file p5 allows you to structure your code along the logic of a processing sketch with a setup() (runs once) and draw() (loops continuously). The only difference is that preceding “void” is replaced by “function”. In the setup a new canvas is placed using a variable used to then call p5 methods and access their elements from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://p5js.org/reference/#/p5.Element&quot;&gt;library&lt;/a&gt;. See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/processing/p5.js/wiki/Beyond-the-canvas&quot;&gt;github repository&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above example sketch is the one included in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://p5js.org/get-started/&quot;&gt;getting started&lt;/a&gt; section of the website, so I need to get a bit more creative, but its a good simple sketch to try and integrate. The only difference is that in the setup I needed to assign a variable to createCanvas() to point it towards my located div. Alternatively I could have set up the canvas and position it within the javascript, but I prefer to use CSS to take care all of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a slight quirk with my approach that means the p5 sketch extends slightly further in width that the div wrapper. I attempted to use the div client width as the width of the canvas but the two do not quite correlate. If you have any advice on this please tweet me on @chrisbamborough&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;canvasDiv&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;myCanvas&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;divWidth&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;myCanvas&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;clientWidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sketchCanvas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;createCanvas&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;divWidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;450&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;sketchCanvas&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;parent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;myCanvas&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;draw&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;mouseIsPressed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fill&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fill&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;255&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ellipse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;mouseX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;mouseY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;40&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;40&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;keyIsPressed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;clear&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2016 05:45:00 +1000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/04/30/P5InJekyll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.chrisbamborough.com/blog/2016/04/30/P5InJekyll.html</guid>
        
        <category>Creative</category>
        
        <category>Code,</category>
        
        <category>p5.js</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
